Hi everyone.
안녕하세요
So the reason I'm so fired up about week seven is that this is the time when we actually start to build
7주 차에 제가 이렇게 흥분한 이유는 우리만의 모델을 구축하기
our own proprietary model.
시작했기 때문이죠
It's when we start to build our own AI, and we are looking to build something that we're going to try
우리만의 인공지능을 개발하기 시작하는 시기예요 개척자 모델과 경쟁할
and make to compete with frontier models or yes, even we're going to try and see if we can outperform
수 있는 제품을 만들려고 해요 적어도 몇몇 개척자 모델보다 나은 제품을 만들려고
at least some frontier models.
노력하죠
Now, the reason that that's even possible is that we are trying to solve one particular specific problem
그게 가능한 이유는 데이터가 많은 특정 문제를 해결하려 하기 때문이죠
where we have a lot of data, and so we can take potentially a model that is significantly smaller than
그래서 프런티어 모델보다 훨씬 작은 모델을 쓸 수 있어요
We can take something like an 8 billion parameter model.
80억 개의 매개 변수 모델을 사용할 수 있어요
And by making it very good at one focused task, we can compete against the, the, the enormous the
한 가지 집중된 작업에서 뛰어난 성과를 내면 거대한 거대 기업과 경쟁할 수 있습니다 GPT
Giants, the Giants like GPT four zero.
40 같은 거대 기업요
Because even though GPT four has trillions of parameters, it's designed to do so many different things,
GPT 4에는 수조 개의 매개 변수가 있지만 다양한 용도로 설계되었기 때문입니다
including writing witty poems about presidential Candidates.
대선 후보에 관한 재치 있는 시를 쓰는 것도 그중 하나죠
We are not going to be able to do any of those things, but we are going to try and get really, really
이 모든 걸 할 수는 없겠지만 제품 가격을 예측하는 데에
good at predicting prices of products.
정말 최선을 다할 거예요.
That's going to be our thing.
우리만의 방식이죠
That's our business problem.
그건 우리 사업상의 문제예요
That's what we're setting out to solve.
그걸 해결하려고 해요
The first step in this is to decide which model we're going to use as our base model for fine tuning,
첫 단계는 어떤 모델을 미세 조정의 베이스 모델로 쓸지 결정하는 겁니다 시간을
and that's something that's worth taking time on, because it's going to be so obviously pivotal to
들일 가치가 있는 일이죠 우리가 만들 것에 결정적인 역할을 할 테니까요
You can think of it in itself as like a one massive great hyper parameter.
그 자체로 하나의 거대한 하이퍼 매개 변수라고 생각할 수 있죠
We can try a different base model and see how that performs.
다른 기본 모델을 시험해 보고 어떻게 되는지 보죠
And as part of that, we're going to have to decide whether we take the original pre-trained version
그 일부로 그 훈련받은 모델의 원래 버전을 쓸지 결정해야 해요
of that model, the very base model.
바로 그 기본 모델요
Sometimes people use the word foundation model to to describe that, as opposed to the one that's been
사람들은 그걸 설명하기 위해 파운데이션 모델이란 단어를 쓰는데
fine tuned for chat purposes that sometimes called the instruct variant, which is the one that's expecting
채팅 목적으로 잘 만들어진 건 반대로 변환이라고도 하죠 사전이나 사전 목록을 기대하는
a dictionary or a list of dictionaries with a user prompt system, prompt user assistant, and so on.
거예요 사용자 프롬프트 시스템이나 사용자 보조 같은 게 있는 거죠
That style of input, which you remember, gets turned into just a series of tokens separating out different
입력 스타일은 프롬프트의 다른 섹션을 분리하는 토큰 시리즈로
sections of the prompt.
바뀌죠
So we've got to make a decision about that.
그래서 결정을 내려야 해요
And there are of course, pros and cons.
물론 장단점이 있죠
Um, and then once we've done that, we should then take the base model as it is off the shelf and see
그 작업이 끝나면 기존의 기본 모델을 가져다가 우리 과제와 어떻게
how that does against our challenge, because, you know, we see whether we're already in a position
맞물리는지 봐야 해요 우리가 이미 프런티어 모델과 경쟁하는
where we are competing with the frontier models.
위치에 있는지 알 수 있으니까요
And even if we're not competing with frontier models, remember that this is going to be free of charge,
우리가 개척 시대 모델들과 경쟁하지 않더라도 무료로 진행될 거라는 걸 기억하세요 적어도
or at least it will be the cost of us.
비용은 우리가 부담해야죠
Running computes so we won't have to pay API costs when we're running our own open source version of
계산을 실행해 API 비용을 내지 않아도 되죠 고유의 오픈 소스 버전 모델을 실행할
the model.
때요
So even if we're in the right territory, there's still many reasons why we should use open source.
따라서 올바른 영역에 있다 해도 오픈 소스를 써야 할 이유는 여전히 많아요
Even before we talk about making it into a proprietary model specialized for this particular business
이런 특정 비즈니스 문제에 특화된 독점 모델로 만들자는 얘기가 나오기 전부터요
So anyways, with that in mind, it's time for us to talk about which model to use.
어쨌든 그걸 염두에 두고 어떤 모델을 사용할지 얘기해보죠
Uh, first of all, we need to decide how many parameters to use.
우선 매개 변수를 몇 개 쓸지 정해야 해요
And, you know, it is probably a case that more is more.
많을수록 좋은 것 같아요
More parameters is going to give us a better shot at, uh, solving the problem.
매개 변수가 많을수록 문제 해결에 도움이 돼요
Well, particularly in a world as we have it, where we have a lot of training data, we have 400,000
특히 훈련 데이터가 많은 현재 세계에서는 400,000개의 예가
examples.
있어요
So we've got tons of training data.
훈련 데이터가 아주 많아요
It's not like we're limited in that regard.
그런 면에서 한계가 있는 건 아니잖아요
And we could always generate more if we wanted to.
원하면 언제든 더 만들 수 있어요
So really our constraint is going to be, uh, it's going to be the amount of memory capacity that we
그래서 제약 조건은 우리가 가진 메모리 용량의 양이 될 거예요
have.
작은 상자에 넣을 거예요
And so we pretty much already know at this point that we can we can get in about an 8 billion parameter
지금까지는 이미 알고 있었어요 약 80억 개의 매개 변수 모델을 얻을 수 있다는 것을요.
model.
70억에서 80억 매개 변수죠
We won't be able to go much more than that.
그 이상은 못 가요
And whilst there are some small parameter models, very small uh, like like Gemma goes down to, I
작은 매개 변수 모델이 있긴 하지만요 아주 작죠 젬마 같은 경우 20억에서 30억
think a 2 or 3 billion parameter version.
개의 매개 변수 버전일 거예요
Uh, we'll take a look in a second.
잠시 후에 살펴보죠
Um, the, uh, we're probably going to want to, to take eight as the, uh, the largest possible model
8대를 가져가려고 해요 저희 예산에 맞는
that will fit into the boxes that we can afford.
가장 큰 모델로요
So that's going to be our approach when it comes to the base or the instruct variants.
그게 저희가 베이스나 변형을 만들 때 접근하는 방식이죠
There are pros and cons and it's something to experiment with.
장단점이 있는데 실험해 볼 만한 거예요
Generally speaking, if you're fine tuning specifically for one problem where you have a particular
일반적으로, 한 가지 문제에 대해서만 미세 조정할 수 있습니다 특정 프롬프트를 이용하고 있고 특정
prompt that you'll be using and expecting a response in a particular way, then you might as well start
방식으로 응답을 기대한다면 기본 모델로 시작하는 것이 좋습니다
with a base model, not an instruct variant, because you don't need to apply things like system prompts
변종은 아닙니다 시스템 프롬프트나 사용자 프롬프트 같은 것을 적용할 필요가 없습니다
and user prompts because you're just going to be training it for one purpose anyway.
한 가지 목적으로만 훈련시킬 것이기 때문이죠
So you might as well just take a base one and fine tune it, so that all it's really good at is that
그러니 기본을 하나 골라서 미세 조정하세요 그 작업에만 정말 잘하도록요
So that's the kind of default answer.
그게 기본 대답이에요
Now there are some benefits to starting with the instruct variant.
변종으로 시작하면 좋은 점이 있어요
One of them is that it's very good.
하나는 아주 맛있다는 거죠
It's already been trained to recognize things like a system prompt and the user assistant interaction.
시스템 프롬프트나 사용자 보조 상호 작용 같은 걸 인식하도록 훈련받았죠
And you can use that to your advantage by using the system prompt to sort of tee it up in a certain
이를 장점으로 활용할 수 있습니다 시스템 프롬프트를 이용해
way to to frame it, to be working, uh, to be, uh, taking a persona, uh, rather than having to
특정 방식으로 틀을 잡고 작업하는 거죠 인격에 의존하지 않고 훈련 데이터를 통해
rely on it, learning that persona through all of your training data.
인격을 익히는 거예요
So there are some situations where the instruct variant is a better starting point.
그래서 변형 구성이 더 나은 출발점이 되는 상황도 있어요
Uh, now, for us, my instinct is that base is the better starting point, because we've got such a
제 직감으로는 기초가 더 나은 출발점입니다 훈련 데이터와 목표에
set structure that we're going to be using for all of our training data and for our objective.
사용할 정해진 구조가 있으니까요
Um, and I've in fact tried both and base did do slightly better than the instruct variant, but they
사실 둘 다 써봤는데 밑바탕이 개별 제품보다 조금 더 잘 나왔어요 하지만 막상막하였죠
Uh, you could also try both and see if you get the same results as me.
어, 둘 다 해 보시고 저랑 같은 결과가 나오는지 확인해 보세요 Get up
Uh, but uh, I would think it would be more normal in our kind of situation, when you have one particular
하지만 이런 상황에서는 더 정상적일 것 같아요 하나의 특정 작업이 있는데
task and you don't need to be applying system prompts and the like that you would start with the base
시스템 프롬프트를 적용할 필요가 없을 때요 그런 경우 기본 변종에서
variant.
시작하죠
But with that introduction, let's head over to the Hugging face, uh, open leaderboard and take a
소개를 마쳤으니 이제 안아주는 얼굴로 넘어가죠 오픈 leaderboard에서 모델들을 살펴볼게요
look at some models.
HOLO